Hello and welcome back. I just want to spend a few minutes
【未完成版本】 大家好 欢迎回来 我将花几分钟的时间
explaining some of the concepts that we learn about curves on the plane, but now
讲解一些我们学过平面曲线的概念
surfaces in 3D. so its going to be a much shorter video
而后介绍三维空间的曲面概念 所以这个视频比之前的会短很多
than the previous one, and we're going to be discussing Surfaces instead of curves.
我们不讨论曲线 而会讨论曲面
Just a couple of concepts. Surfaces are really beautiful, and we
但只讨论一些概念 曲面真的很优美
could spend years, some people spend all their life, studying surfaces, but once
我们可以花几年时间去研究它 有些人甚至花一生去研究
again, we only have time for a few key concepts that will help us to understand,
不过再提一下 我们只有一点点时间来讲解一些主要的概念 它们将帮助我们理解
for example, active surfaces, how to do segmentation of volumes in three
例如 活动曲面 如何对三维图像做分割
dimensional images. again, just a few concepts.
再提一下 这些仅仅只涉及到一些概念
We have a surface us on a surface. Basically, we are only going to be
这里有一个曲面 基本上 我们只讨论
talking about, talking about surfaces in three dimensions,
三维空间中的曲面
and basically on the surface we can draw curves. Here we have curves.
在这个曲面上 我们可以画上一些曲线 这里有几条曲线
Now basically, each one of these curves is in 3D now, so you have to have X, Y
现在 每条曲线都是三维的 所以必须有X Y Z三个轴
and Z. But we basically have the surface.
然而 我们看到这个曲面
Imagine that the surface is basically floating on a plane.
想象这个曲面漂浮在一个平面之上
So the way we parameterize the surface is now with two parameters, U and V.
因此 我们用两个参数来表示这个曲面 分别是 u 和 v
Remember, for curves, we have only one P, for surfaces we have two.
请记住 我们只用了一个参数P来表示曲线 对于曲面 我们需要两个参数
So we basically are on the plane. So we have U and V.
所以 对于一个平面 我们有两个轴 u轴 v轴
On the plane, for each U and each V, we have a X coordinate, Y coordinate and Z
在平面上 每一个u和v都对应了一个x坐标 y坐标 z坐标
coordinate, and that's how we represent a surface.
我们通过这种方式来表示一个曲面
Two parameters, three coordinates in curves we have one parameters,
用两个参数来表示三个坐标 对于曲线 我们用一个参数
two coordinates, because we were on the plane we can have curves in 3D that would
表示两个坐标 而且由于在一个面上 我们可以用一个参数
be one parameter, three coordinates, for example this one.
表示三维空间的曲线 表示三个坐标 就像这条曲线
So that's a surface. Now let's define normal area, and things
以上讲的是曲面 现在 我们来定义法线 面积元
like that on the surface. But if we have curves, we can take
还有平面上其他类似的概念 如果讨论的是曲线
derivatives, as we were doing on the plane.
我们可以对它求导 就像我们在平面上做的那样
So we can take a derivative, according to the U parameter and according to the V
我们可以对参数u和参数v求导
parameter. So we can basically be on a curve and
所以 在一条曲线上
basically say, let's just take a derivative of that curve, according to U
我们可以在方向u和方向v上 对它求导
and according to V. If we do the cross product of these two
如果对这两个矢量做矢量积 (cross product)
vectors, we get the third vector perpendicular to these two.
我们可以得到第三个矢量 它和这两个矢量垂直
Once again, basic algebra. So the normal is the cross product of the
这些仅仅只基础的代数知识 而法线就是这两个向量的矢量积
two. So, the derivative of S according to U is
所以 S在方向U上的导数是平面的一条切线
tangent. The derivative S according to V is
S在方向V上的导数也是平面的一条切线
They will define a plane which is tangent
这两条切线构成了一个平面
to the surface at this point. If we do the cross product between them,
这个平面在这个点上和曲面相切 如果对两个矢量求矢量积
we get a normal to the surface. And again, we are going to normalize that
我们可以得到平面在这个点的法线 而且对它进行归一化
because we're interested in unit length normals.
因为我们感兴趣的是单位法线
So we have derivatives which means time change and then the normal if we have
我们得到了导数 它们表示了切线 还有得到了法线
derivatives we can for example define the element of area we know that then once we
如果求得了导数 我们可以定义面积元 我们知道
have two vectors. The determinant of the matrix composed by
一旦有了两个矢量 就可以用这两个矢量组成的矩阵的行列式
those vectors, basically defines the area of the parallegram that we see here.
定义这里的平行四边形的面积
So if that is infinitesimal, we have elements of area.
如果它是无穷小的 我们就得到了面积元素
If that's integrated across multiple, across long regions, then we have the
如果对很多这样的区域求和 我们就能够得到整个面积
total area. So, same type of concepts.
这些概念和之前学的是相同的类型
We have length on the plane, we have areas here.
在平面上可以求得曲线的长度 在这里可以求得曲面的面积
We also have length, because the surface, it's just a lot of curves, nothing else
我们也可以求长度 因为曲面就是有很多曲线完美地组合而成
than that, nicely organized. So once again, here is the
没有别的 再提一下
parameterization, and here is the normal. Let's see the example of something that
这是曲面的参数表达形式 这是法线 我们来看一个大家熟悉的例子
you are familiar with, which is basically graphs. The same way that we saw graphs
曲面图 和我们见过的平面图一样
on the plane, we can see graphs in three dimensional space.
我们可以在三维空间里看到曲面图
So we have a coordinate system, X,
我们有一个坐标系 x轴
Y, and Z, and basically we define a graph that's again floating on space.
y轴和z轴 我们定义一个曲面图漂浮在空间中
So our parametrization is XU, equal to U. Basically X is one of the parameters, YV
所以 参数表达式中的 x=u  x是参数之一
equal to V, and then Z basically the height of the surface, or in this case
y=v 并且 z表示曲面到坐标平面的高度 在这种情况下
the graph or the function, is just a function of these two, a particular case.
它是一个函数 仅仅是 x y 的一个函数
Think about an image, for example. An image is a particular surface, it's a
举一个特别的例子 想象一幅图像 这幅图像是一个特别的曲面 它是个函数
function. So, the plane of the image is X and Y, or
图像的平面是x和y 或者u和v
U and V. The grey values of the image is the
图像的灰度值就是高度 也就是z
height means Z. So you can think about images as
所以 你可以认为图像是一个曲面
surfaces, in a particular case, as functions or
在特定情况下 是个函数或者曲面图
graphs. And that's a very interesting
这是个很有趣的解释
interpretation. We can basically compute things.
我们可以计算一些东西
We can compute the normal of an image, as we saw in the previous slide.
我们可以用前面讲到的方法 计算图像的法线
Basically we treat the image as a surface.
我们把图像当做一张曲面
We take derivatives, we compute the normal of an image.
对它求导 计算出图像的法线
So we bring a lot of concepts of differential geometry into image
因此 我们在图像处理中引入了许多微分几何学的概念
processing. Now what about curvatures?
那么 曲率又是怎么表示的呢？
So the basic idea is very simple. Once again we have curves. If you have a
其实 基本思想很简单 对于曲面上的一条曲线
curve, you can take first derivative according
你可以通过弧长对其求一阶导数
to our link. This is a curve in 3D, basic same concept and second derivative.
它是三维空间的一条曲线 但是基本概念是相同的
Second derivative would basically view the curvature of that particular curve
二阶导数表现了特定曲线的曲率
that you do. For example, this one.
比如说这条曲线
No sometimes you want to project that curvature, remember first derivative is
有时候 你想要投影这个曲率 请记住 一阶导数表示了
tangent, second derivative is perpendicular to the curve, not
切线 二阶导数和曲线垂直
necessarily to the plane. You have a curve there's a lot of things
但不一定和切面垂直 一条三维的曲线可以有
that can be perpendicular to that, so you can take it and project it to the normal
很多线和它垂直 因此 你可以将二阶导数投影到法线上
or the perpendicular of the plane if you wish.
或者切面的垂线上
And that's basically something that's called the normal curvature.
这样 我们就把它叫做法曲率
So you take the curve, you take second derivative, that gives you a vector and
所以 你取一条曲线 求它的二阶导数 得到一个矢量
you project that vector into the perpendicular to the surface.
把它投影到垂直曲面的矢量上
But that's about basically maybe you are thinking about a curve but if I have a
但是 这些是考虑一条曲线时的情况 如果你考虑一个点
point. Let me just make that here.
我在这标记一下这个点
If I have a point on the surface, they're are multiple curves.
如果曲面上有一个点 那么曲面上就会有很多条曲线
On the surface that go through that point so look at all the curve.
穿过那个点 就像这些曲线一样
There are multiple of them. So what exactly defines the curvature at that
有很多条曲线 那么我们应该如何定义那个点的曲率呢？
point? It turns out that there is one of these
事实上 这些曲线中有这么一条曲线
curves, that when we treat it at a curve and we compute the curvature, it's the
我们把它当做一条曲线 然后计算它的曲率
smallest possible. And there is another curve that is the
它的曲率可能是最小的 还有另外一条曲线
largest possible. So we basically define the principal
它的曲率可能是最大的 我们可以
curvatures of a surface in the following way.
用下面的方法定义曲面的主曲率
You're in a point, and you basically try all the possible curves on the surface
对于曲面上的一个点 你可以尝试曲面上过那个点的所有曲线
that go around that point, and you basic compute the curvature.
计算它们的曲率
Now we are talking about curves. This curve has a curvature.
现在 我们讨论的是曲线 这条曲线有一个曲率
You compute all of them.
这条曲线也有一个曲率 我们计算出所有曲线的曲率
There's one, which is the minimal,
这样就会有一个最小的曲率值
and one which is the maximal. Sometimes there's more than one.
和一个最大的曲率值 有时候 这些值对应的曲线会不止一条
For example a sphere might have, basically have more than one, all
比如一个球面 过一点有多条曲线
directions are the same. But you have, for regular surfaces, you
在不同方向上 它们的曲率值大小相同 不过 对于一般的曲面
have at least one which is the max and there which is the min, and those are
你至少会得到一个最大值和一个最小值
called the principal curvatures of the surface and I just tell you a bit of
它们被称为曲面的主曲率 我要提一下其他一些性质
extra information. The curve that gives you the max and the curve that gives you
拥有最大曲率的曲线和拥有最小曲率的曲线
the min are perpendicular to each other. Now, and there's way of computing this.
两者相互垂直 而且 有很多方法可以计算这些
You don't really have to try all the curves.
你不需要尝试所有的曲线来计算这些
There's way of computing. I'm just taking about concepts here.
有很多方法可以计算这些 这里 我只是讲解了一些概念而已
So, there's one direction which is max. The other is min.
因此 存在某个方向的曲率 它的值最大 还存在另一个方向 它的值最小
Think about the cylinder. When you cut a cylinder, perpendicular to
大家可以想象一下圆柱 当你垂直于它的轴做一个切面
its axis, there is one direction that you basically
也就是这个方向的曲线 可以组成一个圆
get a circle. What's a curvature there?
那么这样的曲率是多少呢？
One over the radius, we know that. There's another direction in the
我们都知道曲率是半径的倒数 还有另一个方向的曲线
direction of the cylinder that you get a straight line.
沿着圆柱的方向 可以得到一条直线
What's a curvature there, we know, it's zero.
我们知道 这种情况下的曲率是0
So in one direction we get one over the radius.
所以 在某个方向上 我们得到的曲率是半径的倒数
That's a maximum the other you get zero. That's a very nice thing.
它是最大值 在另一个方向上 得到的是0 这个很简单
it's a surface that in one of the directions,
曲面在某一个方向上
THE curvature is actually zero. So, on a curve, there is only one
它的曲率等于0 而 一条曲线只有一个曲率
curvature. You're turning, and there's only one
因为在选择方向时 曲线上只能选择一个方向
direction to go on the curve. On the surface, you can go in multiple
但在曲面上 你可以选择很多方向
directions. And there will be one which is the
在某个方向上 曲率最大
maximum direction that will curve the most, one is the minimal, where will
曲面弯曲得最厉害 存在另一个方向 曲率最小
curve would curves the least. And actually, that basically completes
曲面弯曲程度最小 事实上 由这两个曲率就可以得到
which is called the min curvature, which is the average of both of them, and the
所谓的平均曲率 (Mean curvature)  它是两个曲率的平均值
Gaussian curvature which is the product of them.
另一种是高斯曲率 (Gaussian curvature) 它是两个曲率的乘积
So what's a Gaussian curvature of a cylinder?
那么圆柱面的高斯曲率是多少呢？
Zero. At every point in one direction,
它等于0 圆柱面上任何一点 从某个方向看
basically it's a straight line. So it's zero, and there is a lot of
它是一条直线 所以高斯曲率是0
beautiful differential geometry on surfaces, a lot of it due to Gauss.
曲面上有很多精妙的微分几何学知识 都很高斯 (Gauss) 有关
Really beautiful, but these are the basic concepts. So you have the same as on the
相当精妙 不过这些都是基本概念 所以它们对于
plane, curving,
平面上的曲线 还有曲面上的曲线 是类似的
the curving of the surface, but we have curving in multiple
只不过 在曲面的不同方向上都有曲线
directions. We have the max, the min, and normally
我们可以得到最大曲率和最小曲率 通常
people say, instead of taking the max and the min, let's take the average and the
人们喜欢用两个的平均值和乘积 而不是直接用最大最小
product. From this you can of course, from the
当然 通过平均值和乘积值
average and the product of course you can go back to the max and min, or vice
你仍然可以计算出最大值和最小值 反之亦然
versa. So these are basic concepts of surface
以上就是曲面微分几何的基本概念
differential geometry. Again, we have normals, curvatures, the
再提一下 我们讲了法线 曲率
same kind of concepts that we had for planar curves.
这些概念和平面曲线差不多
So now after these two videos, one relatively longer than the other.
现在 通过这两个视频的学习 上一个视频比这个长多了
Your an expert in differential geometry. And at least you have the tools to
你应该对微分几何学有了一定的了解 至少你已经掌握了基本方法
understand what is coming next. Which is deformation of curves, meaning
来帮助理解接下来的内容 曲线的变形 意味着
deformation of shapes, and their relationship of that with active
形状的改变 还有活动轮廓和
contours, active surfaces, and even with image denoising and image enhancement as
活动曲面之间的关系 甚至和图像降噪 图像增强之间的关系
we are going to see it. Remember,
我们将学习到这些内容 请记住
images are surfaces, so we can treat them with the tools that
图像就像曲面一样 所以 我们可以用上刚刚学到的知识来处理图像
we, we just learned. They have curvatures, they have normals,
我们可以用到曲率 用到法线
they have the same concepts of differential geometry.
用到微分几何学中的概念
I'll see you in the next video. This is getting real, really, really
在下个视频中 我们学到知识非常刺激
exciting. I hope you're having fun.
我希望大家学得愉快
See you very soon. Thank you.
【未完成版本】 到时候再见 谢谢大家